in this video we're going to focus on
banked curves so here's a question for
you
a car is traveling on a frictionless
banked curve of radius 200 meters
if the curve is banked at an angle of 15
degrees
at what speed should the car travel in
order for it not to slide up or down
so let's draw a picture
so banked curves look like an incline
but it's different
this of motion involved
so
i'm gonna draw a box
now imagine this box as being a car
let's call this
the x direction
and let's call this the y direction
and the car
is moving forward
in the z direction
now you want to make a distinction
between this type of motion
and a regular incline which we covered
earlier where a box simply slides down
in the x direction
it's not moving in the y direction
and so you want to make that distinction
now
if the car
is moving too fast
without friction being present
it's going to slide off
it's going to slide up
the
bench curve
in that direction if it's moving too
slow
it's going to slide down towards the
center
so there is a certain speed
at which the car
will not slide up or down
our goal is to find that speed
now i want to make a distinction between
the free body diagrams
of a regular incline and a bank to curve
so in a typical incline
we would have a normal force
perpendicular to the surface
as usual
and as a component of the wave force
that will accelerate the block downward
so this is the weight
and here is
a component of the wave force this side
is
mg cosine theta
and this is
mg sine theta
now on a regular incline the normal
force is
equal to mg times cosine theta
so let's say if we had an angle of 45
degrees
cosine 45
is 0.7071
so that means that the normal force
supports 70.71 percent of
the weight of the object
in the regular incline problem
now on the banked curve
the situation is different
the normal force is still directed in
the same direction
it's still perpendicular to
the surface
however
it supports more than the weight of the
object
the normal force
has a component
that is directed towards the center of
the circle so keep in mind
this object is traveling
in circular motion
it also has a y component so i'm going
to call this
f
and x
and let's call this f
n y
now we still have to deal with the
weight of the object which is mg
now turns out that this angle here
is equivalent to this angle
now if you want to see it
let's say that this angle
i'm running out of space but let's say
it's 60 that means this angle is 30
and this line is perpendicular to that
line
which means
this angle must be 60 as well
and the normal force is perpendicular to
the surface so that's another 90 degree
angle which means this is 30 and this
has to be 60. so these two are
equivalent to each other
hopefully you can see that because i am
short in space
there's not much space to work there
now we need to realize is that
this force
the y component of the normal force
is equal to the weight of the object
when friction is not present
so fn y is equal to mg
now fny
is fn cosine
if you recall from sohcahtoa hopefully
you took trig cosine theta is equal to
the adjacent side divided by the
hypotenuse
so that's fny over fn
so fny if you rearrange it by cross
multiplying
is n
cosine theta
and so these two are equal to each other
so fn cosine theta
is equal to mg
which means that the normal force
is mg divided by cosine
so make sure you see the difference
between these two equations
in a regular incline problem the normal
force is mg times cosine theta
but for a bank curve it's mg divided by
cosine
and if the angle is 45
like in this example
1 divided by cosine 45 or 1 divided by
0.7071
is
1.414
so the normal force supports
141.4 percent
of the weight force
at this
angle so clearly
the normal force on a bend curve
is doing a lot more
work
than
the normal force on
the incline it's putting a lot more
effort
now you might be wondering why is it so
different
what's the reason well if we look at an
incline
the normal force only has to support
just a portion of the weight the mg
cosine part of the weight
the reason being is a portion of the
weight force
is used
to cause the object to slide down
the incline
now in this example
the normal force
has to support the full weight of the
object
and not only that but it has to provide
the centripetal force
necessary to keep the object traveling
in circular motion
and so that's why the normal force is a
lot larger on a bank curve than on a
regular incline
but now let's get back to the problem
so let me erase
a lot of stuff
so i'm going to redraw the incline
here's our vehicle
here's the normal force
and this is the x component of the
normal force
and this is the y component
so keep in mind whatever angle we have
here is equivalent to this angle
so the y component of the normal force
as we said it's fn times cosine theta
which means that the x component
has to be fn sine theta
sine
is associated with the opposite side
cosine is associated with the adjacent
side with respect to the angle that
you're considering
and let's not forget about the weight
force
now keep in mind if there's no friction
there is an exact speed for the car not
to slide up
the incline or the bank curve or down
the bank curve
and this is important to understand if
the car is moving too fast if it's
moving greater at that design speed
the car is going to slide up the incline
if it's moving too fast
if it's moving too slow
it's going to slide down
the bank curve
so just make sure you understand that
because that's important
so we need to find a speed at which it's
going to maintain its current position
how can we find that speed
so let's focus on the forces
in the y direction
so we have the net force in the y
direction that's equal to
this upward force
and because it's going in the positive y
direction it's going to be positive fn
cosine
and this force is going in a negative y
direction so
negative mg
now there is no net acceleration in the
y direction
the car is not being lifted off the
ground and it's not going straight
through the ground
it's maintaining its position in the y
direction so therefore the net force in
the y direction we could say is zero
so now i'm going to add mg to both sides
and so mg
is equal to fn cosine theta
and if you divide both sides by cosine
you'll see that the normal force
on a bank curve when no friction is
present it's equal to mg divided by
cosine
on a regular incline it's mg times
now what about the forces in the y
direction i mean not the y direction but
the x direction
let's see what we can come up with
the only force in the x direction
is f n sine theta the x component of the
normal force
now there is a net force in the x
direction
because there is an acceleration
towards the center
of the bank curve
and that acceleration
based on this diagram it's pointed in
the negative x direction
so this is x
and this is the y direction
now i should add a negative sign
to f n sine theta because this is going
in the negative x direction
now the net force is the mass
times the acceleration
that's the centripetal acceleration
because
it causes the
the car to move
within circular motion
and it's going in the negative x
direction so i'm going to put a negative
sign in front of it
just so you can get used to the process
of
setting up these types of formulas
now in this example the two negative
signs will cancel
and the centripetal acceleration is v
squared over r
so this net force is really this
centripetal force
and that's equal to fn
sine theta
now what i'm going to do
is i'm going to replace
the normal force with mg over cosine
theta because
they're equal to each other
so let's take this and insert it into
this equation
and so what we're going to have now is
mv squared over r
is equal to mg
divided by cosine
times sine
now we could divide both sides by m so
we can cancel it
and sine divided by cosine
is tangent if you remember your trig
stuff so v squared over r
is equal to g
times tangent theta
now our goal in this problem is to
calculate the speed
so we need to get v by itself
so let's multiply both sides by r
and so we can get rid of this
and so v squared is equal to rg tangent
theta
and now what we need to do at this point
is take the square root of both sides
so here's the equation v
is equal to let's just get rid of some
stuff now
let's just write this bigger
so v is equal to the square root
of rg
tangent theta
so this equation
allows us to calculate the speed
at which the car
can maintain its position
in a bank curve without sliding up or
down and when no friction is present
so the radius of curvature it's 200
meters
g is 9.8 meters per second squared
and the road is banked at an angle of 15
degrees
so that's going to be tangent 15. so
make sure your calculator is in degree
mode
so the answer that you should have
is 22.9
meters per second
so if the car maintains
that speed
it's not going to slide up or down
it's simply going to travel forward
let me draw that better
let's say if the car
speeds up and travels at 30 meters per
second
it's going to go up the incline
if it goes at 50 meters per second it's
going to go down the incline
so if you view it
just from a flat surface like this
if it travels at 30 it's going to go up
this way
if it travels at 15 it's going to go
down that way
but if it maintains a speed of 22.9 it's
going to stay where it is
now let's move on to part b
what angle should the road be banged
for a car to travel at a speed of 30
meters per second without sliding up or
down in the absence of friction
so if we can increase the angle
we can increase the speed
at which your vehicle
can safely travel the bank curve without
sliding up or down
so that new angle has to be greater than
15 degrees
because at an angle 15 degrees the speed
was 22.9 meters per second
so if we want to increase the speed to
30 we need a much larger angle so let's
go ahead and calculate the angle let's
square both sides
so v squared is equal to rg
tangent theta
and now let's divide both sides by rg
so v squared divided by rg
is tangent
now to get theta the angle we need to
take the arc tangent of both sides
so the angle is going to be arc tangent
or inverse tangent
of v squared
divided by rg
so this is the equation that you want to
use
if you need to find a banking angle
when no friction is present
so it's going to be arc tangent
v squared or 30 squared divided by the
radius which is 200
times 9.8
30 squared or 30 times 30 is 900
and 200 times 9.8 that's 1960.
so this is going to be arc tangent
900 over 1960
and so that's going to give you an angle
of 24.62
degrees or we could say 24.7 let's round
it
so at this angle
the car can safely travel at a speed of
30 meters per second without sliding up
or down
the bench curve
you